Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 7: Tablature and Drum Notation
We are going to use the lead sheet now,
to create a simple arrangement
I have copied the music into a new score
Next we’ll enter the notes for the guitar,
bass and drums in the 1st measure
You can enter notes on either the standard staff
or the tab staff
And since they are linked, they show up on both staves
To enter notes in the tab staff, click the 1st measure
Then enter the Note Input mode
Choose the note value with the mouse
You can't use the shortcut here
You are going to use the up and down arrow keys
to move to the different strings
We are going to move to the 5th string
And then you type the fret number,
using the number keys
To advance use the right arrow
Now I'm doing this a little bit differently and notice that
I have only entered the notes on the 5th string
Now I'm going to use the arrow keys
to move to the 6th string
And then I'm going to place an E, an open note,
typing 0 on each downbeat
Next I will enter the 8th notes in the bass,
using step entry
Drum notation can be introduced using the keyboard
or the MIDI keyboard
Select the drum staff, then enter Note Input mode
You see the mapping of the drums
on the bottom of the screen
We will enter a simple beat with hi-hat,
snare and kick drum
In drum notation the hi-hat and the snare
will have the stems going up
The base drum will have the stems going down
MuseScore will handle this automatically
We will enter the hi-hat first
Enter Note Input mode
and then select the 8th note
You notice then in the drum map
that the hi-hat has been assigned the shortcut G
So we can just type G and it will enter the note
You can also type any key on the MIDI keyboard
While the note is selected in the drum map,
and it will enter as well
To add the snare drum,
use the left arrow key to move to beat 2
You’ll see down in the drum map,
that the shortcut for snare drum is A
Hold the Shift key down and type A
Then move to beat 4 and do the same thing
Now for the kick drum
You notice that the kick drum note is shown in green
This means it will be entered in voice 2
Use the arrow key to move to beat one
Type 5 for quarter note
and then B
Now type 4 to change that to an 8th rest and 0
Now type B again
type 5
and then B one more time
So now is our basic rhythm section parts entered,
where we did create the rest of our arrangement