Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 9 - Repeats and Endings, Part 2
Now we take a look at some other types of repeats
It's pretty common,
when you have measures repeating exactly like this
to use one measure repeat instead of writing it all out
So I'm going to select and delete all of those measures
And I'm going to Repeats & Jumps Palettes
and drag a one bar repeat
into a rhythm section instruments
Now I select that measure, use the R key to repeat it
We can do that also in measure 6 and 8
Now let's have a solo section
We use our rhythm section parts and so,
just copy the first 12 measures
and click in measure 15
and paste it
Over there is probably not a bad idea
to put a double bar line in, to make things clear
Next we will fill the saxophone part with slashes
Go up to the Edit Menu
Select Tools, Fill With Slashes
After the solo we return to the head,
before jumping to the ending
I want to place a double bar at the end of the solo
And we will go to the Repeat Palette
and select “D.S. al Coda”
to take us back to the first measure measure
Then I put a sign in measure 1
We jump to the coda after measure 8
So put the “To Coda” sign there
And we haven't actually created a coda yet,
but we know where it's going to be
So it's going ahead and move down there
and we will place the coda sign
at the first empty measure
Finaly I'm going to copy a couple of measures
and the word coda
And we go ahead
and enter a couple of notes to take us out
One last thing we should do is copy the chord symbols
to the guitar and the bass
Select the first chord symbol, right click
and then Select, All Similar Elements
Now thats going to cause a little bit of a problem
because of these last two
and so I'm going to hold the command key
and select those to delete them from our selection
Now I can copy and paste these
Actually I'm going to cut them from the tenor
cause I don't need them there
I’m going to select the first measure here
and then I select the first measure of the bass
and past them in
and I will do the same thing
for all of the solo section
We have a couple of extra measures at the end
Let's go ahead and get rid of those
Select those and go to the Edit menu, Measure,
Delete Selected Measures
There are arrangements also though