Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 6 - Text, Lyrics and Chords
Next we need to add chords and lyrics to our melody
In the course of writing the lyrics,
I decided to change the title
So let's double click
I'm going to change that from
"Blues for a while" to "Blues for Muse(Score)"
Now let's enter the lyrics
Lyrics are attached to notes
I'm going to zoom in just a bit to make it easier
Select the first note,
and then right click underneath it
Select the text submenu
and you see there lyrics down at the bottom
Notice the shortcut Cmd + L / Ctrl + L
While we are at it, you should notice the
shortcut for the chord symbol
We'll use that a little bit later
So now select lyrics
Type the first word 'I'
Then press the spacebar to move to the next note
We continue to enter the next couple of notes
The word 'blues' extends into the next note,
the tied note
So to move to that, we are going to put an
extension and that is Shift + Dash or Underscore
We do it once and then we do it one more time
for the note that we are extending to
And that will take us to the next note
We are continuing entering the rest of the phrase
In the same way
Now 'MuseScore' is a two syllable word
To move to the next note use the Dash key
And again we need our extension here
So press Shift + Underscore twice
The second phrase is the same as the first
And as with notes, copy and paste is faster
Select any of the lyrics, and then right click
to select all similar elements
Now everything is selected
Type Cmd or Ctrl + C to copy it
Click the first note of the second phrase
and then type Cmd or Ctrl + V to paste it
Now click the first note of the last phrase
Type Cmd+L again and enter the rest of the lyrics
Chord Symbols are entered in much the same way
Click the first note of the first measure
And remember our shortcut Cmd + K
And we can enter our chord
We can then click the first note
of the fourth measure
use the shortcut again and type that in
And right here we also do the same thing
You can also use the spacebar to advance
The last chord is a turnaround chord
so we'll put that in parenthesis
You'll notice that MuseScore has done
a pretty good job in fixing the layout already
Let's go ahead and delete this last measure
Go up to the edit menu, select measure,
delete selected measures
The backspace key won't work here
Now that's perfect, we've got four measures
on each line and our lead sheet is done