Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 8 - Repeats and Endings, Part 1
In this lesson we will take what we've done so far
and create an arrangement using copy,
paste and various types of repeats
It will make it easier to follow along,
if we turn on measure numbers first
Go up to the Style menu
Select General
Then check “Header, Footer, Numbers”
and then at the bottom tick “Measure Numbers”, “Interval”, and then set it to 1
Now we fill up the rhythm section
and we will do the head
MuseScore has a very well hidden command,
that will let us copy and paste at the same time
Let's select all of my measures for the rhythm
section and if I type the key R
it copies and pastes it all in one stroke
So let us do that for all 12 measures
Our score is going to get a little large
And so I think it will be easier to work
if we switch to continuous view
Now we use the transpose tool
to create a chord progression
Going to measure 5, I am going to select
measure 5 and 6 on the guitar and bass
and go up to the Notes menu and select Transpose
We will transpose it up by interval
and it's going up a Perfect Fourth
At measure 9 we will do the same thing,
but we going to transpose it up a Perfect Fifth
And then we need to transpose
measure 10 and measure 12 as well
It's pretty common to play the head of a blues twice
So let's go ahead and create first and second endings
We start out by using our repeat command,
selecting measures 11 and 12 and type R
Next, go to the Barlines Palette
and select the backward repeat
and drag it to measure 12
Go back to measure one and select the forward repeat
and drag it to measure one
Now we go to the Lines Palette
I will select the first ending and drag it
to measure 11
Now I need this to extend the measure 12
So I'm going to doubleclick and then hold
the Shift key down and press the arrow key
Don't just drag it, it won't work,
it won't play back correctly
Now we can drag the second ending to measure 13
We need to do just a little bit of touch up
Our first ending should have the pickup note
added in the melody
So we go ahead and change that
And then also I'd like to go ahead
and make the sound a little bit more like a turnaround
by putting a rest on the downbeat
on the guitar and the bass
Just click on those and type 0