Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 10 - Articulations, Dynamics and Text
With all of the notes and chords entered,
we can now turn our attention to express the details
All of these entries come from the palette
There are few also found in the Add menu as well
Some also have shortcuts assigned
The pallete entries are attached to notes
Select the note first
and double-click the item in the pallete
Let's start by entering some dynamics at the beginning
You can adjust the dynamics by dragging them
But it's usually better to go over here
and use the inspector and use the offsets
Staccato is one of the articulations,
that has a shortcut assigned
Click on a note and type Shift+S
it's a toggle so if you type Shift+S again, it'll be removed
You can assign more than one articulation to a note
Put the staccato back and go over here,
to the Articulations & Ornaments palette
and while that note is still selected,
I'll double-click the accent and it will place it there too
Fermatas are also in the articulations palette
We can enter them into all staves at once
by selecting the notes
and then double-clicking the fermata
You see that there is an extra one
because we have two voices in the drums
Just click on that and delete it
While we are here, let's go ahead
and add a role to the last symbol
Select a note, select the Tremolo
Double-click
And let's add an arpeggio to this chord
I'd also like to add a decrescendo right here
on this very last line
And it's a line, so I select the palette, double-click it
and then use Shift+Right to extend it
to the end of the line
Slurs are also in the Line palette
and are entered in the same way
Double-click and then use the right arrow key
to extend it to the end of the line
You notice that there are handles here
and this will let you adjust the ark
A various types of text can be entered from the palette,
the Add menu or using a shortcut
One special text entry is Swing
Enter it the same way you enter other items
from the palette
What’s next is special, is the effects playback
Now let's add a tempo marking
Select the Tempo palette
Select the first note and double-click a tempo
and now we can double-click it to edit it
We don't actually want to see that,
it's going to be too cluttered
so we just click the visible button in the inspector
and it will not print out
Finally let's add a rehearsal mark
At the beginning of the solo, select the first note
and we use the shortcut Cmd/Ctrl-M
for the rehearsal mark
and then type B for our letter
So now all of the entries are done
and the score is almost complete
In the next lesson we make it fill in the page nicely
and take a look at the parts