Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 11 - Layout and Parts
With everything entered,
we can now turn our attention to the layout
Let's start by setting the view to one or two pages,
depending on your screen size
You can see we have a number of problems
The systems are not centered on the page
Our chord symbols are overlapping the stems here
The first ending is split between two systems,
that is usually not a good idea
And then we have
the dreaded hanging system at the end
Let's start with the chord symbols
They are little to far away from the staff
We can adjust that globally
Go up to the Style menu, select General
Chord Symbols, and then reduce
the default vertical position to one and a half spaces
Click Apply, then OK
That solved some of the problems
But there is still not enough space
between the bass and the tab-staff
We could increase that globally too,
but then it would affect all staves
Since we only need to increase the space
between those two staves
we use the tools in the Breaks & Spacers palette
There are two spacers tools:
one for up and one for down
Select the spacer up
and then drag it into the middle of the staff
They will automatically increase the space
You have to do it for each system
If you need more space, double click on the spacer
Click on the handle and drag it up or down
The next step is to reduce the size of the notation
That should solve a lot of the other problems
Select page settings from the Layout menu
and reduce the scaling
until you see three systems on the first page
Now, while we are here, let's go ahead
and increase the page margins
Let's do the odd page first, page 1,
and increase that to 15
and on the even page, page 2, we are going
to increase it to 25
Click OK
And you can see that most of our problems
have been taken care of
But it would be better if it used all of both pages
Let's start by moving the coda to a new system
In the breaks and spacers palette
Click on the system break tool
and drag it to the measure right before the coda
Now use the same tool to move measures around
So that we have the melody on one page
and the solo on the second page
And then balance it out
It's common to indent a coda
Select the first measure of the coda
Go up to the Add menu, select Frames,
Insert Horizontal Frame
A last step in layout is to look it over carefully
for any overlapping entries
or other things that should be adjusted
The title and the composer need to be moved
We click on that, use the horizontal offset
Center it
Move it up a little bit
or move the composer down a little bit
Now zoom in and scan the score
Don't worry about any of the non-printing characters
like spacers or page breaks
To create parts, select Parts from the File menu
Click New All and then OK
You have a separate tab now for each part
The parts are dynamically linked to the score
Any changes to entries on the part
will be reflected in the score and vice-versa
But the layout including the offset is independent
Parts will be saved automatically,
when you save your file too
This is the last video
in the introductory series on MuseScore 2.0
I hope you have enjoyed it
and now you are on your way to be a power user
We still be posting tips and tricks along
the way so we hope to see you again soon