Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes.
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program.
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen.
Lesson 5 - More Input Ideas
We’ve already looked at ways to enter notes
using the mouse, keyboard, and a midi keyboard
But there are even better ways
to get notes into MuseScore
In this video we are looking some ways
to finish our melody very quickly
Let's start by taking a look at the entire melody
If you look closely, you notice that the rhythm
of the first and second phrases are identical
but the pitches change
You also see that first half of the third phrase
has the same rhythm
We start by using copy and paste
First we need to break up the rest,
to make beat 4 visible in measure 4
Let's click on that whole rest, type a 6
to break it in a half notes
and then select a 2nd one and type 5
to turn it into quarter notes
I usually like to zoom in
when I'm doing selecting work
So I'm going ahead and zoom in to 150%
And now, what I want to do is
to select this phrase and copy it
So click on the pickup measure
hold the shift key down and select all that measure
Now type Cmd+C or Ctrl+C to copy it
Click on that last quarter rest
and then Cmd+V or Ctrl+V to paste it
We are going to to the same thing in measure 8
So now, we have 3 identical phrases
If this were a Riff-Blues, we'd be done
But we still have to change the notes
To do this, we use the repitching tool
Click the 1st note of the 2nd phrase
Type N to enter note input mode
and then click the repitch tool right next to it
Now play the correct pitches for phrase 2
and the first half of phrase 3
Don't chose any note values
When finished, click the repitch tool again
to return to input mode
The melody ends with a measure of triplets
Let's enter those now
If you are still in note input mode,
press the Esc key
And then select measure 11, hold the shift key
and select measure 12
Press the Backspace key to delete the notes
Click the whole rest
Now enter input mode again and type 6
then type Cmd+3 for a triplet
And you'll see, that we have now a quarter note triplet
Play the notes
Right now, we have to do Cmd+3 again
for the next triplet
Press 6 first
And then our last note, the whole note
There is one more very important method of
inputting music in MuseScore I need to mention
Importing
MuseScore has long supported the import and export
of more file formats than any other program
The list of supported formats is shown on the screen
There are thousands of these files
available for free in the internet
The results you get from importing each type
of those files will vary greatly
Some will be almost ready to use
and some need so much work
that it's pretty much useless
In general MusicXML files will provide the
best results that require the least amount of editing
But there are usable files in all formats